残酷な天使のように 少年よ 神話になれ
青い風が今 群れのドアを叩いても
私だけをただ見つめて 微笑んでるあなた
そっと触れるもの 求めることに夢中で
運命さえ まだ知らない 痛いけな瞳
だけどいつか気づくでしょう その背中には
遥か未来 目指すための羽があること
残酷な天使の転生 窓辺からやがて通り
ほとばしる熱いパッドスで 思い出を裏切るなら
この空を抱いて輝く 少年よ 神話になれ
ご視聴ありがとうございました
Mankind cannot live alone.
Although you, yourself, are always unique.
That is why life is hard.
That is why life is sad and empty.
Thus you want the close physical and mental presence of others.
That is why we wish to become one.
The human soul is made of weak and fragile elements.
The body and mind are made of brittle components as well.
And so, via the instrumentality, mankind must fill and complement each other.
Must you ask?
Because there's no other way to exist.
Why do you exist?
Maybe I exist to find out why I exist.
For whom do you exist?
For myself, of course.
Maybe for myself.
Are you happy being alive?
I don't know.
Of course I'm happy!
Are you happy being alive?
I don't want to do anything except to be happy.
Do you hate being sad?
I don't like it.
Do you hate enduring pain?
Is that why you run away?
Yes.
Do you blame me?
What's wrong with running away from something that hurts?
I mustn't run away.
Tell me why you mustn't run away.
Because escaping from reality can be painful.
Even though you're running from something more painful?
I couldn't bear it.
As long as you know what the pain is, it can be endured.
That's correct.
If the pain is too harsh, you can escape it.
If you really hate it, Shinji, you can still run.
No, I won't.
I'm tired of escaping.
Yes, I mustn't run away.
That is true.
That is because you are now aware that running only brings you more pain.
This is because running away can be far worse.
That's why you do not wish to escape.
Because if you run away, nobody will respect you.
Don't leave me alone.
Don't deserve me.
I'm begging you.
There he goes again, depending upon others who do everything for him.
That's a sad survival mechanism, isn't it?
So what?
It's better than being left all alone.
Because you fear being hurt.
You try to make yourself believe that, don't you?
You're not the only one who gets hurt, Shinji.
Everybody feels pain.
You aren't the only one.
It's just easier for you to think that it's true, isn't it?
Shut up!
I don't care!
Why should I?
Nobody cares about me!
Once again, you've abandoned all sense of self-value, of self-worth.
I have nothing.
There you go again, saying that you have no worth at all.
Do you believe that by not expecting anything, you won't get hurt either?
Is that how you sustain your pathetic ego?
By asking others to praise you?
Nobody accepts me.
That's not true.
You just believe that is so.
And so that's why I must pilot the Ava.
Again, that is merely your point of view.
You've been trying to convince yourself that you're worthless since the very beginning.
But I have to!
I've got to do it!
No, that's not true.
You don't have to.
No, you just think you do.
No, you're wrong.
My life is pointless otherwise.
And that's why you pilot the Ava?
Piloting Ava gives me an identity, a purpose.
I had no value before I became a pilot.
The fact that I now pilot an Ava justifies my presence here.
I have no other value.
No other value at all.
I perceive no value in myself.
I hate myself.
You little worm!
I hate you!
Me too!
I hate you too!
I hate everything about you!
I'm sorry, but I hate you!
I hate you!
I hate you.
I hate everything about you.
Oh, Shinji, I hate you.
See? Everyone hates me!
Every person in existence must hate me!
No, that's just what you imagine.
Yes! But that must be it, because I hate myself!
Because you hate yourself, no one respects you.
I hate you! I hate you!
I hate everything!
They praise me.
They're nice to me.
When I pilot the Ava, they treat me better.
Other people are being nice to me for the first time.
Which is your true feeling?
I don't know. Or is it perhaps that both are my true feelings?
So that's why you pilot the Ava?
Because I have no choice. I only have the Ava.
Otherwise, you could not retain your own identity.
In fact, Ava Unit 1 is part of your sense of being.
But if you depend only on the Ava, then the Ava will become your only identifier.
Ava will become your only value.
Without that value, you, the real you, will be erased from this existence.
I don't care. I had no other value to start with anyway.
I was learning to play the cello, but that didn't help me either.
You just didn't discipline yourself. I didn't have to do that.
But now that I can pilot the Ava...
No. Soon you may lose your identity, as I have. Soon you may lose Ava and your self-worth.
I pilot it because that's all I can do.
Rain. Dark shadows of gloom hang above me. That's how I feel. This isn't how I want it to be.
The setting sun. The ending of life. This is not how I wish it to be.
Morning. The beginning of a day. Another terrible day. I wish this wasn't the way it is.
Blue sky. Something warm. Something unfamiliar. Something that fills me with horror.
I don't want this. I don't want it to be this way.
I hate everything!
What do you want, Shinji?
Don't let me please!
What I fear is...
What I want is...
Can I stay next to you?
May I stay here?
Do you like me?
Do you want to go where your mother is?
No.
Don't you want to go be with your father?
No, I don't.
Why?
Because I'm afraid of being hated.
Because my identity might start to disappear.
What is it that you wish for?
What is it that you want?
You're very insecure, aren't you?
To become secure, I have to have value.
I want to be worth something.
I want to be worth enough to attract the attention of others.
But your value is something you have to find for yourself.
You have to find it, Shinji.
I have no value without it.
My life is worthless without it.
Then what am I?
What am I?
Wait, what is this?
This is me.
This is the shape that lets others recognize me as myself.
It is my symbol for myself.
This is...
And this is as well.
Representations.
Everything is merely a description, not the real myself.
Everything is simply a shape, a form, an identifier to let others recognize me as me.
But then, what am I?
Is this me?
My true self?
My fake self?
What is it that I am?
You are you.
There is little difference between how you interpret yourself and how the others interpret you.
Right.
My clothes.
My shoes.
My room.
These are all parts of what makes up myself.
These things are connected through your consciousness.
So what I think is me, is me.
What I recognize as self, is myself.
I'm no more and no less than the sum of my self-awareness.
But I don't understand myself.
Where am I?
What am I?
Nobody understands me!
What are you, stupid?
Of course nobody understands you.
Nobody can ever understand you.
The only one who can take care of you and understand you is...
You, yourself.
So you must take care of yourself.
But I still don't understand myself.
I don't even know what it is that makes me myself.
How could I love myself?
You are still unstable.
That is the present you.
And the people around the present you.
And the environment that surrounds the present you.
None of these elements of reality last forever.
Time continues to flow and time brings change.
Your world is in a state of constant change.
You are capable of change anytime your mind perceives these changes.
What is this?
A world of nothing?
A world with nobody in it?
This is the world of perfect freedom.
Freedom?
Perfect freedom.
A world in which you have no restriction.
Is this really freedom?
Yes.
This is what it is.
However, this world has nothing in it.
Unless I do something?
Right.
Unless you do or think of something.
But I don't know what to do or think of.
He is uncertain.
He has no self-image to orient himself.
There's nothing solid here.
It is a world in which there are no obstacles.
No anything.
This is a world in which you can do anything you wish.
And yet, you are still afraid, aren't you?
Don't you know what it is that you want to do?
What should I do?
Let me give you a restriction.
There.
Now you have a top and bottom.
But you have lost a degree of your freedom.
You may no longer fly.
You must stand upon the earth.
But now you feel easier, don't you?
Because you have less to trouble your mind.
And now you can walk.
This is happening because you will it to be.
Is this my will?
This world with the floor is the only thing around yourself.
But now you can move around anywhere you wish to within it.
You could even turn the world upside down if you wanted to do that.
And your perspective within your world is constantly changing.
It changes with the passage of time.
You can change yourself as well.
Because the thing that forms your shape is your mind and its interaction with the world that surrounds you.
You can do anything here.
Because this is your world.
This is the shape of your reality.
Oh yeah.
What is this?
An empty space?
An empty world?
A world where nothing exists but myself?
But with only myself, I have nothing to interact with.
It's as if I'm here, but not here at all.
It's as if I'm slowly fading out of existence.
Because only you are here.
Only myself?
Without others to interact with, you cannot truly recognize your own image.
My own image?
That's right.
In the act of observing others, you may find and recognize yourself.
Your self-image is restrained by having to observe the barriers between yourself and others.
And yet, you cannot see yourself without the presence of others.
Because there are others, I can perceive myself as an individual.
If I am alone, then I will be the same without others.
For if this world is only of me, then there will be no difference between me and nothing!
By recognizing the differences between yourself and others, you establish your identity as yourself.
The very first other person is your mother.
Your mother is a different individual.
Right. I am me and she is she.
But are you really sure that the perceptions of others form my true self?
It's true, Shinji Ikaru.
Has it taken you this long to realize that?
What an idiot!
It's about time you got up, you idiot.
Oh, it's you, Asuka.
What the hell does that mean?
Can't you appreciate that I went to the trouble of coming to wake you up personally?
I don't hear any words of appreciation for your oldest childhood friend.
Thanks.
Let me sleep a little more.
Hey! Get up, you!
It's time to get up, you dork!
You stupid pervert! I didn't mean to get that up!
I can't help it. It's morning.
I gotta take a whiz or something.
Oh, my. Asuka's so sweet to come pick him up every morning.
And he doesn't appreciate it.
Hmm. Is that so, dear?
Yes, dear. And you have to get ready, too.
I'm always ready, dear.
Gosh, you are just like Shinji.
Mm-hmm. You ready?
Anytime.
I am the one who gets complaints from Professor Fuyutsuki if you're late for the meeting.
That's true. He's your biggest fan.
Oh, you! Cut that out and get ready.
Yes, dear. She must be obeyed.
Hurry up!
Geez, you're such a pain in the ass sometimes.
Is this what happens when you start your period?
What? What did you say?
Ow!
Mrs. Akari, we're leaving now.
Bye. See you later, Mom.
See you, sweetie.
Come on, dear. Put the newspaper down.
All right.
Hey, isn't a new student starting today?
Yeah, that's right. Since this city's going to become the new capital, there are a lot of people moving in.
It's no wonder we're getting so many new kids.
Oh, that makes sense. I wonder what she's like. Oh, I hope she's got a great butt.
Oh, crap! I'm late! I can't be late for the worst bag!
I'm sorry. I'm really in a hurry, kid. I'm really sorry! Bye, dear!
Wow! So, did you see her panties then?
Well, it wasn't a good look, really. Just a little flash.
Oh! I can't believe it that you're the one who has all the luck!
What'd you do that for?
Exactly what were you just talking about, Mr. Suzuhara?
It's time to put that idle butt of yours to work. Change the water into flower vases.
Oh, she's mean.
Did you just say something?
Poor Toji's so carpet-bagged. It's sad, isn't it?
Look who's talking.
Hey, are you saying that I'm...
I'm merely reporting it back.
How so?
It just is. Accept it!
Hey, why do you treat me like this?
Hey, that hurts, you idiot!
Oh, the calm, the peace and tranquility.
Oh, yeah!
Miss Visado, our teacher!
Oh, she's gorgeous!
Oh, yeah!
Oh, look at that!
Oh, she just...
Oh, yeah!
Just look at those three stooges.
Have they no shame?
All right.
Stand up.
Bow.
Sit down.
Listen up, dudes.
We've got a new blue-haired babe here to introduce herself.
My name's Rei Ayanami.
How's it hanging?
No!
Oh!
You're the jerk who was staring at my panties!
Hey!
What do you mean by that?
You're the one who was flashing them, you know.
Who are you and why are you defending him?
Are you riding his baloney pony?
No!
We're just really good childhood friends.
You shut up!
Be quiet, you two.
We're in a class, not a bar.
Hey, this is more entertaining than class.
Go on.
I want to see how this turns out.
Hey, Shinji!
You didn't tell me you were a kid.
No!
I was soたい.
I know.
No!
We're just really good childhood friends.
You shut up!
Be quiet, you two.
We're in a class, not a bar.
Hey, this is more entertaining than class.
Go on.
I want to see how this turns out.
Hey, Shinji!
You didn't tell me you were getting it with Asuka.
I see, so this is another possibility.
Another possible reality.
This current myself is the same way.
It's not the true myself.
I can be any way I wish to be. I see.
And myself, who is not an Ava pilot, can exist as well.
If you take that into consideration,
then perhaps this world isn't that bad.
Still, the reality itself might not be bad,
but I could still hate myself.
But it's your mind which takes reality and separates it
into what's bad and hateful.
It is only the mind which separates reality from truth.
Any new position from which you view your reality
will change your perception of its nature.
It's all literally a matter of perspective.
There are as many truths as there are people.
But there's only one truth that is your truth.
That's the one that's formed from whatever point of view
that you choose to view it from.
It's a revised perception that protects you.
That's true, and one can have a perspective that's far too small.
However, a person can only see things from the perspective
that they choose to see them from.
One must learn to judge things via the perceived truths
that one receives from others.
For example, sunny days make you feel good.
Rainy days make you feel gloomy.
If you are told this is so, then that is what you believe is so.
But you can have fun on a rainy day as well.
Your truth can be changed simply by the way you accept it.
That's how fragile the truth for a human is.
A person's truth is so simple that most ignore it
to concentrate on what they think are deeper truths.
You, for example, are simply unused to what it is to be liked by others.
You've never learned how to deal with fearing what others feel about you,
and so you avoid it.
But don't the others hate me?
What are you, stupid?
Haven't you realized it's all in your imagination, you mega-dork?
But I hate myself.
One who truly hates himself cannot love.
He cannot place his trust in another.
I'm a coward.
I'm cowardly, sneaky, and weak.
No.
Only if you think you are.
But if you know yourself, you can take care of yourself.
I hate myself.
But...
But maybe...
Maybe I could love myself.
Maybe my life could have a greater value.
That's right.
I am no more or less than myself.
I am me.
I want to be myself.
I want to continue existing in this world.
My life is worth living here.
Yeah!
Congratulations!
Congratulations.
Ah, thank you all.
Thank you.